BASHA SHAIK

OBJECTIVE

Seeking a challenging position as a director of engineering in a technology company which can utilize my skills, technical, management and leadership, and provides me ample opportunity to apply all my organizational experience I gained over time, to grow and to contribute in the most effective manner.

SUMMARY

~20 years of experience in Software Architecture, Design, Development, Testing, Performance testing, Scalable Distributed Systems, Inter-Operability, Product Planning, Release Management, System Engineering and Research in Wireless, Mobile App Development & Regional Customization, Network Management, Smart Home products and Distributed Online Services for Gaming domain.

12+ years of Project Management, Waterfall & Agile, Risk Management, Resource planning

10+ years of People Management, Performance Management, Career development, Mentoring, Compensation Planning, Talent planning, Hiring, Onboarding, Training, building high performing teams, Managing managers 2.5 years of overseas experience

KEY SKILLS

Programming: C, C++, Shell scripting, Java (Basics), Scala (Basics)

OS: Unix, Linux, Windows 7,8,10

Cloud: AWS, Google Cloud

Databases: MySQL, SQLite3, Redis, Mongo DB

Web Development: Node.js, Apache, Nginx, React.js

Mobile Development: Symbian, Android

DevOps: Docker, Kubernetes, Mesos

Project Management: MS Project, JIRA, Confluence, Waterfall, Agile

Other Tools: GIT, Perforce, Clearcase, Clearquest, Eclipse, VSCode, Visual Studio, Graphite,

Grafana

DOMAINS

Performance Engineering. Scalable distributed Systems, Protocol Stack development, Device drivers, Call Processing features development for RAN,

System Engineering for Motorola CDMA RAN, IEEE Standardization process, Smart Energy Profile Design, Development & IOT, Mobile App Development, Localization and Regional customization, Global Launch & Language implementation

WIRELESS

WIMAX, LTE Concepts, NFC, VLC (Visible Light Communication), IrDA, Smart Energy, CDMA, EV-DO, CDMA RAN (Radio Access Network), ZigBee, TCP/IP

PROFESSIONAL ACHIEVEMENTS

- Certified Scrum Master (CSM) (Member ID: 000389557)
- Participated in many IOT (Inter-Operability Test) events for conformance compliance of Samsung Smart Home Product and played a key role in obtaining the certification from ZigBee Alliance
- Submitted 3 patents in radio resource management and softer handoff in Distributed
 Wireless Communication system based on WiMAX.
 - US20090016303 / 10-2007-0069648 (KR) Method for performing softer handover in broadband wireless communication system
 - 10-2007-0034203 (KR) Method and apparatus for radio resource allocation in broadband mobile communication system
 - 10-2007-0038029 (KR) Apparatus and method for radio resource allocation under the consideration of QoS in broadband mobile communication system using multiple input multiple output
- Attended IEEE Plenary Session, 2007 in San Francisco to understand the trends in 802.15.3c (mm Wave alternative PHY) and BAN (Body Area Networks)
- Received Idea of the Month award for the month of May, 2006 from Motorola Networks Innovation Board, Schaumburg, USA.
- Submitted few Think-Tank (Motorola internal knowledge database) ideas in Push-to-Talk features.
- Received BRAVO awards 2 times for high pro-activeness and ownership leading to a high
 productivity in the CDMA system engineering (Call Processing) work and for having very less
 defect density in CDMA Mobility Manager Product.
- Received BRAVO awards 2 times for high pro-activeness and ownership leading to a high
 productivity in the CDMA system engineering (Call Processing) work and for having very less
 defect density in CDMA Mobility Manager Product.
- Received Core Staff Award for the years 2011 & 2012 in Samsung for the excellent performance.

Page | 2 Basha Shaik

WORK HISTORY

DIRECTOR OF ENGINEERING, ELECTRONIC ARTS (EA) GAMES INDIA PVt LTD, HYDERABAD

Feb 2014 - Till Date

R&D PROJECT MANAGER, NOKIA SIEMENS NETWORKS, HYDERABAD

Sep,2012 – Jan, 2014

SENIOR TECHNICAL MANAGER, SAMSUNG INDIA SOFTWARE OPERATIONS, BANGALORE

Mar, 2009 - Aug, 2012

RESEARCH ENGINEER, SAMSUNG ELECTRONICS, SUWON, SOUTH KOREA

Nov,2006 - Feb, 2009

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER, MOTOROLA, HYDERABAD/BANGALORE

May, 2002 - Sep, 2006

EDUCATION

B. TECH, NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (Earlier REC), WARANGAL

B.Tech in Electrical & Electronic Engineering with 80.8%

DIPLOMA, SMVM POLYTECHNIC, TANUKU

Diploma in Electrical & Electronics Engineering with 85.1%

SSC, ST. AMBROSE HIGH SCHOOL, NIDADAVOLE

10th Std with 80%

PROJECTS SUMMARY

Performance & Reliability engineering of multiple EA game titles: Focus of this project is to analyze and assess the performance of EA's online games. Our group is responsible for performing the game architecture assessment, identifying the bottlenecks and performance improvements, Simulate the player behavior and perform vide variety of load & stress tests to validate the performance of backend servers used in multiple EA games. Assess the game in terms of Stress, Scalability, Security, and Supportability and provide the assessment at multiple phases of game development. Our team is also responsible for the design and development of automation tools to enable the end-to-end tests and monitoring the test runs and generating the reports from highly distributed systems. We also own the live services of the games and responsible for ensuring the stability and performance of the launch.

As a **Senior Engineering Manager** with team size of **17,** handled Battlefield Hardline, Star Wars Battlefront1, Battlefield1, Battlefront2, Battlefield V, FIFA16, FIFA17, FIFA18, FIFA19, NBA16, NBA17, NBA18, UFC-3 game titles. Handled 2 big game franchises of EA from DICE & FIFA Built the team from 10 people to 40 people and improved the effectiveness and efficiency of the team with the process improvements and engineering excellence. Handled all the stake holder communication and exec reporting. Improved the team health by continuously listening to the team's voice via survey's and acting on the pain points. Handled the career development axis for the team and improved it by taking multiple measures like internal brown bags, external trainings, increasing the tech conference participation, coaching & mentoring the senior ICs (>10y exp).

Page | 3 Basha Shaik

NSN Net Act Mediation – Configuration Management: Aim of this project is to design & develop a mediation component to integrate all Motorola LTE network elements into NSN Net Act base platform for the network management operations. As a R&D project manager with team size of 12 handled the development of Configuration Management module (Java, Linux) for this product

Smart Energy Home Gateway & Client: This project involves implementation of Smart Energy Profile (SEP2.0) defined by ZigBee Alliance. SEP2.0 is a home automation, energy management & control profile. The aim is to implement the product straight from the ZigBee specifications and test in inter-operability tests with different company implementations. As a Senior Technical Manager with team size of 6 handled the ZigBee smart Energy home gateway (C++, RESTful web services, Linux) design & Implementation, Implementation of client application (Android) and tested in IoT tests organized by ZigBee Alliance.

Android OS Global Launch: The scope of this project is to create regional variants of the Samsung Android phones by implementing regional, language customizations and implement regional applications. As a **Technical Manager/ Development Lead** with team size of **34** (9 directs, 19 contractors, 6 other's directs) handled South East Asia, South West Asia & Middle East Asia launches. Implemented Indian Languages (14 languages) key boards, RTL languages (Arabic, Urdu, Farsi) key boards, East Asian language (Vietnamese, Thai, Chinese) key boards, RTL support in Android, Indian language support in **Android**, Apps – Mobile Prayer, Mobile Tracker, Prayer Times, Kiblah direction. Also responsible for field testing.

VLC (Visible Light Communication): The aim of this project is to implement the IEEE specifications for the Visible Light Communication protocol (IEEE 802.15.7) to use for the wireless personal area networks (PAN). As part of the project, implemented the communication protocol for VLC by enhancing the IrDA protocol. As a Research Engineer responsible for implementation of the protocol (C++, Linux) as a device driver and participate in IEEE sessions for presenting the results. Also implemented few applications in WinCE, Windows Mobile to demonstrate the usage.

Distributed Wireless Communication System (DWCS): DWCS is a new architecture for the B3G wireless communication system in which the RF antennas are distributed over a geographic region; the RF antennas are connected to the central station using the optical fiber links; the signal processing can be done centrally/distributed among powerful co-located processors. The focus of this project is to propose a scheduling algorithm for a DWCS system based on WiMAX standards. As a **Research Engineer**, submitted few algorithms for scheduling, implemented an application (**C++**) to demonstrate the results, submitted **3 patents** in radio resource management & softer handoffs.

CDMA MOBILITY MANAGER – CALL PROCESSING (MM CP): Mobility Manager (MM) is a network element in the BSC which controls/coordinates the overall call setup, tear down of a call. The MM also controls the radio resource allocation in BTSs. MM performs only control functions (it doesn't process bearer traffic). The MM also performs call control signaling with the MSC. MM also coordinates the handoff process by taking handoff decisions, handoff initiation etc., and The focus of this project is to design, develop (C++, Linux) new features in call processing functional area for CDMA Mobility Manager for Motorola CDMA Radio Access Network (RAN). As a Senior Software Engineer/Software Engineer worked in many new

Page | 4 Basha Shaik

features, enhancements, also worked in System Engineering team for defining requirements, UML modelling of features for the sub-systems of Motorola CDMA Radio Access Network.

IDEN OMC FM RE-ARCHITECTURE: The focus of this project is to do the re-architecture of the fault management for the iDEN (Motorola proprietary) OMC. Operations and Maintenance Centre (OMC) is the heart of network management which monitors and configures the network from a central place. This deals with the Fault management part of FCAPS in network management. The Correlation Services Application developed by this project is used to get all the info of fault management from different network elements and reports to the operator. As a **Software Engineer** responsible for writing test cases, implementing test scripts, execution & reporting of test results.

PROFESSIONAL TESTS

Test	Score	Results Link
Programming with C Certification	8.2	http://www.brainmeasures.com/transcript.aspx?transcriptid=35262
C++ (Easy Level) Test	9.2	http://www.brainmeasures.com/transcript.aspx?transcriptid=35206
C++ (Difficult Level) Test	8	http://www.brainmeasures.com/transcript.aspx?transcriptid=35270
Android (Easy Level) Test	9	http://www.brainmeasures.com/transcript.aspx?transcriptid=35275
Android (Difficult Level) Test	8.8	http://www.brainmeasures.com/transcript.aspx?transcriptid=35278
HTML 4.01 Certification	8.2	http://www.brainmeasures.com/transcript.aspx?transcriptid=35407
JavaScript 1.8 Certification	8.5	http://www.brainmeasures.com/transcript.aspx?transcriptid=35433
Human Resource Certification	8.3	http://www.brainmeasures.com/transcript.aspx?transcriptid=35374
Project Management (Difficult Level) Test	8.5	http://www.brainmeasures.com/transcript.aspx?transcriptid=35376

REFERENCES Available On Request

Page | 5 Basha Shaik